<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Planet SymPy</title>
    <link>http://planet.sympy.org/</link>
    <language>en</language>
    <description>Planet SymPy - http://planet.sympy.org/</description>
    <atom:link href="http://planet.sympy.org/rss10.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://czgdp1807.github.io/gsoc</guid>
      <author>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807)</author>
      <title>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807): Google Summer of Code - What &amp; How?</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://czgdp1807.github.io/gsoc/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am writing this blog entry for sharing some of my personal opinions about this awesome open source program, Google Summer of Code or simply GSoC. I will address various common questions related to this program i.e., What it is all about? and How to achieve it? I hope you can form a reason of yours to participate in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let&amp;#8217;s start with getting to know more about GSoC. Basically, it is a program funded and organised by Google LLC. Google first asks various open source organisations to apply to their portal. After shortlisting, selected organisations are published on &lt;a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/"&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt;. These organisations cover a variaty of areas like mathematics, biology, artificial intelligence, web development and much more. However, software development is at the core of these organisations. Students are then expected to apply to the organisations of their interest. I will be covering more about this part later in this blog entry. Organisations then select some really good applications to work on, the following summers.
So, in short, it&amp;#8217;s much more of like match making between students and organisations for the projects in summer. Note that it is not an internship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let&amp;#8217;s see how you can be a successfull GSoC student. I have mentioned some points below, which you can consider to aim for the same,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selecting the right organisation&lt;/strong&gt; - This is the most important aspect of getting accepted. You should select the organisation which you find most interesting, and most comfortable to work with. For example, I was interested in mathematics and software development, so I went for &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;SymPy&lt;/code&gt;. I would suggest you to go through &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;ideas list&lt;/code&gt; of some organisations which work in your areas of interest. If you find them interesting and you think that you have the right skill set to form a nice project out of those ideas then you have found your &amp;#8220;the right one&amp;#8221;. For example, take a look at ideas of list of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;SymPy&lt;/code&gt; at &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/wiki/GSoC-2020-Ideas"&gt;https://github.com/sympy/sympy/wiki/GSoC-2020-Ideas&lt;/a&gt;. You should be able to find similar such pages for other organisations too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contribute as much as possible&lt;/strong&gt; - Now you have found your right one. Let&amp;#8217;s start fixing some issues. As we know, bugs are the most friendly enemies of any software. They are there with the code always. Many organisations list their issues/bugs on github issue tracker. You can take a look at that list and pick the ones which you can think you can fix by making a pull request. In addition, not all issues are bugs, some are about adding new features to the software too. For example, issues of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;SymPy&lt;/code&gt; are available at, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues"&gt;https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues&lt;/a&gt;. Something similar is available for other organisations too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make a proposal&lt;/strong&gt; - Now comes the hard part of writing a well organised proposal. I will mention here some of the tips to make a good proposal which may increase your chances of getting accepted. First of all, mention about yourself in your proposal, your programming experience, past internships, if any. Then come to your idea which you want to work on in the summers. May be it can be working on improving a module like making the code more efficient or bug fixes. Describe, in detail, the theory related to that idea so that anyone not working in that field should be able to get something out of it. Providing draft code is a big plus. Mention the details of your plan for the official GSoC timeline. There are usually three phases other than the community bonding period. Write about what you will do in each phase. Mention your weekly goals and be &lt;strong&gt;reasonable and practical&lt;/strong&gt;. Optionally, you can write about your plans for the project after GSoC ends officially.
Don&amp;#8217;t forget to discuss your ideas with your potential mentors and community, otherwise it will be like firing a shot in the dark and anything can happen. Follow the application template if your organisation has any. You can take a look at my proposal which is available &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1oIeaROiJyglpbris7X1uZPRE5ZeO0pD1ygCFhBIeATI/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interact with the community&lt;/strong&gt; - Your attitude matters a lot. Be respectful with the members of the community. Follow their code of conduct, and ask your doubts irrespective of the fact that they sound trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that&amp;#8217;s all from my side. Best wishes for your GSoC journey. Don&amp;#8217;t think much about the results until they are announced. Whether you are accepted or not, just know that you have made a difference even by making a simple comment on one of the issues or PRs. :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have provided some resources which might be helpful for developing your skill set for this program,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL6gx4Cwl9DGAKWClAD_iKpNC0bGHxGhcx"&gt;Git tutorials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-0001-introduction-to-computer-science-and-programming-in-python-fall-2016/"&gt;Introduction to Computer Science and Programming in Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/python-beyond-the-basics-object-oriented-programming/"&gt;Object Oriented Programming in Python&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot more of such resources are available at &lt;a href="https://codezonediitj.github.io/resources/"&gt;https://codezonediitj.github.io/resources/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to add something? Just make a PR. Bye.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ishanaj.wordpress.com/?p=122</guid>
      <author>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj)</author>
      <title>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj): Everything about SymPy&#x2019;s Column module</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 19:56:42 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/11/29/everything-about-sympys-column-module/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Column class implemented in &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17122"&gt;PR #17122&lt;/a&gt; enables the
continuum mechanics module of SymPy to deal with column buckling related
calculations. The Column module can calculate the moment equation, deflection
equation, slope equation and the critical load for a column defined by a user.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example use-case of Column class:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="brush: python; collapse: false; title: ; wrap-lines: false; notranslate"&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from sympy.physics.continuum_mechanics.column import Column
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from sympy import Symbol, symbols
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; E, I, P = symbols('E, I, P', positive=True)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; c = Column(3, E, I, 78000, top="pinned", bottom="pinned")
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; c.end_conditions
{'bottom': 'pinned', 'top': 'pinned'}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; c.boundary_conditions
{'deflection': [(0, 0), (3, 0)], 'slope': [(0, 0)]}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; c.moment()
78000*y(x)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; c.solve_slope_deflection()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; c.deflection()
C1*sin(20*sqrt(195)*x/(sqrt(E)*sqrt(I)))
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; c.slope()
20*sqrt(195)*C1*cos(20*sqrt(195)*x/(sqrt(E)*sqrt(I)))/(sqrt(E)*sqrt(I))
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; c.critical_load()
pi**2*E*I/9
&lt;/pre&gt;



&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Column class&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The Column class is non-mutable,&lt;span id="more-122"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; which means unlike the Beam class, a user cannot change the attributes of the class once they are defined along with the object definition. Therefore to change the attribute values one will have to define a new object.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasons for creating a non-mutable class&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt; From a backward-compatibility perspective, it is always possible to  adopt a different plan and add mutability later but not the other way  around. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Most things are immutable in SymPy which is useful for caching etc. Matrix is an example where allowing mutability has lead to many problems that are now impossible to fix without breaking backwards compatibility.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working of the column class:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;strong&gt;governing equation&lt;/strong&gt; for column buckling is:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;figure class="aligncenter"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/qfv6QbVnotFKUPebBoLgBNPjNz5uhN6g2-mbfBzDTR13Cb5z4BkAM7RHGerTtvqEzMzjQFL8r44iYeIVTm0OpYX6f0QWn2rCuz1qxKNVnvM6LHnTX9mfJ9pyBzPmBaFGZPrdiy-p" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;If we determine the the &lt;strong&gt;moment equation&lt;/strong&gt; of the column ,on which the buckling load is applied, and place it in the above equation,  we might be able to get the deflection by further solving the differential equation for &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step-1: To determine the internal moment.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;This is simply done by assuming deflection at any arbitrary cross section at a distance&lt;strong&gt; x&lt;/strong&gt; from the bottom as &lt;strong&gt;y &lt;/strong&gt;and then multiplying this by the load &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; and for eccentric load another moment of magnitude &lt;strong&gt;P*e&lt;/strong&gt; is added to the moment.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-large"&gt;&lt;img alt="" class="wp-image-129" src="https://ishanaj.files.wordpress.com/2019/11/image-2.png?w=641" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple load&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;is given by&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;#160;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;figure class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/mY4nhR2YWfTEITzlL8LFRGnPq2KXPcwbyAGajOWtTkMEBYtTKGya0n4r62RolTLImOGjXazs0RqAjOyAy3K94vrM4G_xZxRKV-GBdG2uULX9qap7xPsgI6ahIY4-tXbx1zYH2LNR" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eccentric load is given by:&amp;#160;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;figure class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/vIfQDO151xRZO2hcDi9pSPeyafqlYmTUBnr_zszHjiZiv07cOA6xnuu__5EslONxpPtQFY5RaUGLXefgY0AtHip6Y6LgANv3XZ1uo790QctxO-Q5qTledCkiTuKzmpaMzJ5LBt-e" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step-2: &lt;/strong&gt;This moment can then be substituted in the governing equation and the resulting differential equation can be solved using SymPy&amp;#8217;s &lt;strong&gt;dsolve()&lt;/strong&gt; for the &lt;strong&gt;deflection y&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applying different end-conditions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The above steps considers a simple example of a column pinned at both of its ends. But the end-condition of the column can vary, which will cause the moment equation to to vary.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Currently &lt;strong&gt;four&lt;/strong&gt; basic supports are implemented:&amp;#160; Pinned-pinned, fixed-fixed, fixed-pinned, one pinned-other free.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Depending on the supports the moment due to applied load would change as:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pinned-Pinned:&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp; no change in moment&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;figure class="aligncenter"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/1rNjrJP3SC6q80sWh9m5-EAj80_YLYSmCECNYMqGh0n24r7EAqP5D8b-joCrvjhV0pnoQeD5EWrcStUufFj8zgHGSIMkk-lrnRPfkxYIJP42RIzh6pCNxthuEP83wWDdhAAZ8I30" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;figure class="aligncenter is-resized"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="218" src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/ki5Fbllhkj2xCcEJiRQxPyuTDlJnQGPfjcvk2GNjnJq5tNd83--zKWRKMck4v9TRx7SINESjNxcmdsXaXh6Le1-fBp8pQLY7pVTy-H_o895Ts_813cFmjlQDfbp34i3RJ3Qvb9RR" width="217" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fixed-fixed&lt;/strong&gt;: reaction moment M is included&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;figure class="aligncenter"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/76IEGW9i83Am9oy_YQC7xm2BVGnEw_BcgM_bQxUgnVdWY4hBpgIIbhE4bG0C8FLpNYpajyoi7F_z8g4uVLfEZOfjv3dQBQ9fvLnIFVZUJvsIaleRSUVA7B1vrQsBj5FY3Ln3H6sx" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;figure class="aligncenter"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/8jXG4tyFMgAzJOanpHqj-d_f37-OkFrntfuhulynED1JjhNT6h_UkHmcAtDyN3Rem95uYIoKuhHUkslItdgIictxZC8dS_6mA9xbW-YxcDgMtyJ-L46UExUNH8VR8octca5v7RWa" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fixed-pinned:&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;figure class="aligncenter"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/zphyPG-BZaoTYFrhY1NVWVza7oBX85d-K3HIDXF02bpcG_3gMsA8zMD-T6UO1X7GX4ssJYeok9IFCILq18GZMDkztjLdA_IA_Otq-qSM30Us22gwqPjPwPnhubYPG3jwtwzq0yML" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; is the restraint moment at &lt;strong&gt;B (&lt;/strong&gt;which is fixed&lt;strong&gt;). &lt;/strong&gt;To counter this, another moment is considered by applying a horizontal force &lt;strong&gt;F&lt;/strong&gt; at point A.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;figure class="aligncenter"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/2Wlvbp1qFbq2p9uf057TCNM7StusOl0J5VAFU-qMQ0BhKTDDdtvP_l-tPgSkC9vmmsAaJd3QR8sEddl_z4LsAqo5FBKEvQNVF6eEssYdex61ENPUb4qWf6nFV7OkZV1Hy5ftDCdJ" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One pinned- other free:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;figure class="aligncenter"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/8vG470fp-wb2CzGMHfR5_chDnr4SqLGM0pAaRXXLSiDklpxXlcCoVOAh8q4dc97ZjWF3GM5-HvPGO1RzRhevUpDxl-cM6pHhztiTxJY-P7Ft04bfciVYK-FnzYJTZr4TvNqqX_wJ" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;div class="wp-block-image"&gt;&lt;figure class="aligncenter"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/eoHyQWUNWNOTFDsofRof215piNvdk9OqETpA4YQWRlp904vpTx69eKRxW12NdAHGxTBNRs63oyP87cMT36DE5judlZWoVeh_7zpP7Vxq5MZ_RkUieecAZGgxSm8Hj5RpKrZIk87g" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;h2&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Solving for slope and critical load&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Once we get the deflection equation we can solve for the slope by differentiating the deflection equation with respect to &lt;strong&gt;x&lt;/strong&gt;. This is done by SymPy&amp;#8217;s &lt;strong&gt;diff()&lt;/strong&gt; function&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="brush: python; collapse: false; title: ; wrap-lines: false; notranslate"&gt;
self._slope = self._deflection.diff(x)
&lt;/pre&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical load&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Critical load for single bow buckling condition can be easily determined by the substituting the boundary conditions in the deflection equation and solving it for &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; i.e the load.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Even if the user provides the applied load, during the entire calculation, we consider the  load to be &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;. Whenever the &lt;strong&gt;moment()&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;slope(), deflection(),&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;etc&lt;/strong&gt;. methods are called the variable &lt;strong&gt;P &lt;/strong&gt;is replaced with the users value. This is done so that it is easier for us to calculate the critical load in the end.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="brush: python; collapse: false; title: ; wrap-lines: false; notranslate"&gt;
defl_eqs = []
# taking last two bounndary conditions which are actually
# the initial boundary conditions.
for point, value in self._boundary_conditions['deflection'][-2:]:
    defl_eqs.append(self._deflection.subs(x, point) - value)

# C1, C2 already solved, solve for P
self._critical_load = solve(defl_eqs, P, dict=True)[0][P]
&lt;/pre&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The case of the pinned-pinned end condition is a bit tricky.  On solving the differential equation via &lt;strong&gt;dsolve()&lt;/strong&gt;, the deflection comes out to be zero. This problem has been described in &lt;a href="https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/07/08/gsoc19-week-6-completing-the-column-class/#more-56"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; blog. Its calculation is handled a bit differently in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17122/files#diff-00c8ee080a295764f42be4b0e448935dR225"&gt;code&lt;/a&gt;. Instead of directly solving it via &lt;strong&gt;dsolve()&lt;/strong&gt;, it is solved in steps, and the trivial solutions are removed. This technique not only solves for the deflection of the column, but simultaneously also calculates the critical load it can bear.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Although this may be considered as a hack to the problem. I think in future it would be better if &lt;strong&gt;dsolve()&lt;/strong&gt; gets the ability to remove the trivial solutions. But this seems to be better as of now.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;A problem that still persists is the calculation of critical load for pinned-fixed end condition. Currently, it has been made as an XFAIL, since to resolve that either &lt;strong&gt;solve()&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;solveset() &lt;/strong&gt;has to return the solution in the required form. An &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues/17162"&gt;issue &lt;/a&gt;has been raised on GitHub, regarding the same.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Hope that gives a crisp idea about the functioning of SymPy&amp;#8217;s Column module.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ishanaj.wordpress.com/?p=113</guid>
      <author>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj)</author>
      <title>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj): GSoC&#x2019;19: Week-12 &#x2013; The Final wrap-up</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 17:10:27 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/08/20/gsoc19-week-12-the-final-wrap-up/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This was the last week of the coding
period. With not much of work left, the goal was to wrap-up the PR&amp;#8217;s.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The week started with the merge of &amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17001"&gt;PR #17001&lt;/a&gt; which implemented a method &lt;strong&gt;cut_section()&lt;/strong&gt; in the polygon class, in order to get two new polygons when a polygon is cut via a line. After this a new method &lt;strong&gt;first_moment_of_area()&lt;/strong&gt; was added in &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17153"&gt;PR #17153&lt;/a&gt;. This method used &lt;strong&gt;cut_section()&lt;/strong&gt; for its implementation. Tests for the same were added in this PR. Also the existing documentation was improved. I also renamed the &lt;strong&gt;polar_modulus()&lt;/strong&gt; function to &lt;strong&gt;polar_second_moment_of_area() &lt;/strong&gt;which was a more general term as compared to the previous name. This PR also got &lt;strong&gt;merged&lt;/strong&gt; later on.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Now, we are left with two more PR&amp;#8217;s to go.
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17122"&gt;PR #17122&lt;/a&gt; (Column
Buckling) and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17345"&gt;PR #17345&lt;/a&gt;
(Beam diagram). The column buckling probably requires a little more
documentation. I will surely look into it and add some more explanations and references
to it. Also, the beam diagram PR has been completed and documented. A few more
discussions to be done on its working and we will be ready with it.&lt;span id="more-113"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I believe that by the end of this week
both of these will finally get a merge.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Another task that remains is the implementation of the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues/17302"&gt;Truss class&lt;/a&gt;. Some rigorous debate and discussion is still needed to be done before we start its implementation. Once we agree on the implementation needs and API it won&amp;#8217;t be a difficult task to write it through.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Also, since the final evaluations have
started I will be writing the project report which I have to submit before the
next week ends.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Since officially the coding period ends here, there would be no ToDo&amp;#8217;s for the next week, just the final wrapping up and will surely try to complete the work that is still left.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Will keep you updated!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thanks! &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_12</guid>
      <author>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807)</author>
      <title>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807): Week 12 - Ending GSoC 2019</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_12/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As the title suggests, with the third phase, the journey of my GSoC 2019 comes to an end. It was full of challanges, learning experiences, and above all interaction with the open source community of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;SymPy&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
In this blog post I will share with you the work done between phase 2 and phase 3, in terms of PRs, merged and open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Merged&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17174"&gt;#17174&lt;/a&gt; : In this PR, Gaussian ensembles were added to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17304"&gt;#17304&lt;/a&gt; : While working on the above PR, I got an idea to open this one to add cicular ensembles to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats&lt;/code&gt;. I learned a lot about Haar measure while working on this.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17306"&gt;#17306&lt;/a&gt;: This PR added matrices with random expressions. The challenging part of this PR was to generate canonical results for passing the tests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17336"&gt;#17336&lt;/a&gt; : This was related to bug fix in &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Q.ask&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Matrix&lt;/code&gt;. Take a look at an example &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17336#issue-304058013"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17387"&gt;#17387&lt;/a&gt; : This PR aims to add support for assumptions of dependence among random variables, like, &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Covariance&lt;/code&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17146"&gt;#17146&lt;/a&gt; : This PR is in its last stages to fix and upgrade the &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt; set and we are finalizing few things, like changes in the output of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;. As planned I was successful at writing exhaustive and systematic tests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, now, time to say good bye! It was a nice experience writing about journey in this blog. If you have read this from the beginning then thanks a lot buddy, and I wish for your acceptance in GSoC 2020. Keep Open Sourcing :D&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://czgdp1807.github.io/z_final_report</guid>
      <author>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807)</author>
      <title>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807): Final Report</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://czgdp1807.github.io/z_final_report/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This report summarizes the work done in my GSoC 2019 project, &lt;strong&gt;Enhancement of Statistics Module&lt;/strong&gt; wth SymPy. A step by step development of the project is available at &lt;a href="https://czgdp1807.github.io"&gt;czgdp1807.github.io&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a third year Bachelor of Technology student at Indian Institute of Technology, Jodhpur in the department of Computer Science and Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project Outline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project plan was focused on the following areas of statistics that were required to be added to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Bonding&lt;/strong&gt; - I was supposed to add, Dirichlet Distribution, Multivariate Ewens Distribution, Multinomial Distribution, Negative multinomial distribution, and Generalized multivariate log-gamma distribution to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats.joint_rv_types&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase 1&lt;/strong&gt; - I was supposed to work on stochastic processes, primraly on Markov chains, including it&amp;#8217;s API design, algorithm and implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase 2&lt;/strong&gt; - I was expected to work on random matrices, including Gaussian ensembles and matrices with random expressions as their elements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase 3&lt;/strong&gt; - I planned to work on assumptions of dependence, improving result generation by &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats&lt;/code&gt; and improving other modules so that &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats&lt;/code&gt; can function properly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pull Requests&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section describes the actual work done during the coding period in terms of merged PRs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Bonding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16576"&gt;#16576&lt;/a&gt;: This PR added &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Dirichlet&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;MultivariteEwens&lt;/code&gt; distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16808"&gt;#16808&lt;/a&gt; : This PR added &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Multinomial&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;NegativeMultinomial&lt;/code&gt; distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16810"&gt;#16810&lt;/a&gt; : This PR improved the API of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Sum&lt;/code&gt; by allowing &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt; as the limits.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16825"&gt;#16825&lt;/a&gt; : This PR in continuation, added &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;GeneralizedMultivariateLogGamma&lt;/code&gt; distribution. This was an interesting one due to the complexity involved in its PDF.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16834"&gt;#16834&lt;/a&gt; : This PR enhanced the &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Multinomial&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;NegativeMultinomial&lt;/code&gt; distributions by allowing symbolic dimensions for them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16897"&gt;#16897&lt;/a&gt; : This was related to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.core&lt;/code&gt; and it helped in removing disparity in the results of special function &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;gamma&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16908"&gt;#16908&lt;/a&gt; : This PR improved &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats.frv&lt;/code&gt; by allowing conditions with foriegn symbols.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16913"&gt;#16913&lt;/a&gt; : This removed the unreachable code from &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats.frv&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16914"&gt;#16914&lt;/a&gt; : This PR allowed symbolic dimensions to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;MultivariateEwens&lt;/code&gt; distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16929"&gt;#16929&lt;/a&gt; : This one was for the &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.tensor&lt;/code&gt; module. It optimized the &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;ArrayComprehension&lt;/code&gt; and covered some corner cases.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16981"&gt;#16981&lt;/a&gt; : This PR added the architecture of stochastic processes. It also added discrete Markov chain to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17030"&gt;#17030&lt;/a&gt; : Some features like, &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;joint_dsitribution&lt;/code&gt; were added to stochastic processes in this PR.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17046"&gt;#17046&lt;/a&gt; : Some common properties of discrete Markov chains, like fundamental matrix, fixed row vector were added.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16934"&gt;#16934&lt;/a&gt; : The bug fixes for &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats.joint_rv_types&lt;/code&gt; were complete and the further work has been handed over to my co-student, Ritesh.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16962"&gt;#16962&lt;/a&gt; : This was continuation of the work done in phase 1 for allowing symbolic dimensions in finite random variables. As I planned, this PR got merged in phase 2, after some changes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17083"&gt;#17083&lt;/a&gt;: The work done in this PR framed the platform and reason for the next one. The algorithm that got merged was a bit difficult to extend, and maintain. Thanks to Francesco for his &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17083#issuecomment-508256359"&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt; for motivating me to re-think the whole framework.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17163"&gt;#17163&lt;/a&gt; : This was one of the most challenging PRs of the project, because, it involved re-designing the algorithm, refactoring the code and moreover lot of thinking. The details can be found at &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17163#issuecomment-510939984"&gt;this comment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17174"&gt;#17174&lt;/a&gt; : In this PR, Gaussian ensembles were added to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17304"&gt;#17304&lt;/a&gt; : While working on the above PR, I got an idea to open this one to add cicular ensembles to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats&lt;/code&gt;. I learned a lot about Haar measure while working.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17306"&gt;#17306&lt;/a&gt;: This PR added matrices with random expressions. The challenging part of this PR was to generate canonical results for passing the tests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17336"&gt;#17336&lt;/a&gt; : This was related to bug fix in &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Q.ask&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Matrix&lt;/code&gt;. Take a look at an example &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17336#issue-304058013"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Miscellaneous Work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section contains some of my PRs related to miscellanous issues like, workflow improvement, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16899"&gt;#16899&lt;/a&gt; : This was a workflow related to PR to ignore the &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;.vscode&lt;/code&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17003"&gt;#17003&lt;/a&gt; : This PR ignored the &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;__pycahce__&lt;/code&gt; folder by adding it &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future Work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following PRs are open and are in their last stages for merging. Any interested student can take a look at them to extend my work in his/her GSoC project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17387"&gt;#17387&lt;/a&gt; : This PR aims to add support for assumptions of dependence among random variables, like, &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Covariance&lt;/code&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17146"&gt;#17146&lt;/a&gt; : This PR is in its last stages to fix and upgrade the &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt; set and we are finalizing few things, like changes in the output of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;. As planned I was successful at writing exhaustive and systematic tests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the above, work on densities of Circular ensembles remains to be done. One can read the Theorem 3, page 8 of &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1103.3408.pdf"&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ishanaj.wordpress.com/?p=105</guid>
      <author>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj)</author>
      <title>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj): GSoC&#x2019;19: Week-11- Heading to the final week</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2019 17:26:54 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/08/13/gsoc19-week-11-heading-to-the-final-week/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the end of this week the &lt;strong&gt;draw()&lt;/strong&gt; function has been completely implemented. The work on &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17345"&gt;PR #17345&lt;/a&gt; has been completed along with the documentations.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the previous blog this PR was an attempt to make the &lt;strong&gt;draw()&lt;/strong&gt; function use SymPy&amp;#8217;s own plot() rather than importing matplotlib externally to plot the diagram. The idea was to plot the load equation which is in terms of singularity function. This would directly plot uniformly distributed load, uniformly varying load and other higher order loads except for point loads and moment loads.&lt;br /&gt; The task was now to plot the remaining parts of the diagram which were:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A rectangle for drawing the beam&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Arrows for point loads&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Markers for moment loads and supports &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Colour filling to fill colour in inside the higher order loads (order &amp;gt;=0).&lt;span id="more-105"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Instead of making temporary hacks to implement these, I went a step further to give the plotting module some additional functionalities. Apart from helping in implementing the &lt;strong&gt;draw()&lt;/strong&gt; function, &amp;nbsp;this would also enhance the plotting module.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The basic idea was to have some additional keyworded arguments in the &lt;strong&gt;plot()&lt;/strong&gt; function. Every keyworded argument would be a list of dictionaries where each dictionary would represent the arguments (or parameters) that would have been passed in the corresponding matplotlib functions.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;These are the functions of matplotlib that can now be accessed using &lt;strong&gt;sympy&amp;#8217;s plot()&lt;/strong&gt;, along with where there are used in our current situation:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org/api/_as_gen/matplotlib.patches.Rectangle.html"&gt;matplotlib.patches.Rectangle&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;-to draw the beam&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org/api/_as_gen/matplotlib.pyplot.annotate.html"&gt;matplotlib.pyplot.annotate&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8211; to draw arrows of load&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org/3.1.1/api/markers_api.html"&gt;matplotlib.markers&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8211; to draw supports and moment loads&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org/3.1.1/api/_as_gen/matplotlib.pyplot.fill_between.html"&gt;fill_between()&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; to fill an area with color&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Another thing which is worth mentioning is that to use &lt;strong&gt;fill_between() &lt;/strong&gt;we would require numpy&amp;#8217;s &lt;strong&gt;arange()&lt;/strong&gt; for sure. Although it might be better if we could avoid using an external module directly, but I guess this is unavoidable for now. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Also, I have added an option for the user to scale the plot and get a pictorial view of it in case where the plotting with the exact dimensions doesn&amp;#8217;t produce a decent diagram. For eg. If the magnitude of the load (order &amp;gt;= 0) is relatively higher to other applied loads or to the length of the beam, the load plot might get out of the final plot window. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Here is an example:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="brush: python; collapse: false; title: ; wrap-lines: false; notranslate"&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; R1, R2 = symbols('R1, R2')
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; E, I = symbols('E, I')

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1 = Beam(50, 20, 30)

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_load(10, 2, -1)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_load(R1, 10, -1)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_load(R2, 30, -1)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_load(90, 5, 0, 23)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_load(10, 30, 1, 50)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_support(50, "pin")
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_support(0, "fixed")
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_support(20, "roller")
# case 1 on the left
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; p = b1.draw()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; p.show()

# case 2 on the right
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; p1 = b1.draw(pictorial=True)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; p1.show()
&lt;/pre&gt;



&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-large"&gt;&lt;img alt="" class="wp-image-107" src="https://ishanaj.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/screenshot-10-08-2019-23_04_45.png" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next Week:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Getting leftover PR&amp;#8217;s merged&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Initiating implementation of Truss class&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Will keep you updated!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_11</guid>
      <author>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807)</author>
      <title>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807): Week 11 - Final touches</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_11/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, the second last week of the project is over and we have decided to improve on the work we have done so far in the last few days. Read below to know more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this week, I worked on, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17146"&gt;#17146&lt;/a&gt; concered with symbolic &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17387"&gt;#17387&lt;/a&gt; related to assumptions of dependence among random variables, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17336"&gt;#17336&lt;/a&gt; which fixed the bug in &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Q.hermitian&lt;/code&gt; the one I told you about in my previous post, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17306"&gt;#17306&lt;/a&gt;, implementing the matrices with random expressions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the last two PRs are merged. Now, coming on to symbolic &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;, I have completed the testing of all the methods except &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;slicing&lt;/code&gt; feature of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;__getitem__&lt;/code&gt;, which I will do in this week. Regarding, the bug in &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Q.hermitian&lt;/code&gt;, well, my code at first, was giving incorrect results due to overriding problems in the logic. Francesco, helped me correct them and it&amp;#8217;s finally in. The major part of the week was devoted to assumptions of dependence. I did some study from Wikipedia, and implemented the class &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;DependentPSpace&lt;/code&gt;. I have kept the class static because it will handle queries of the type, &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;density(X + Y, Eq(Covariance(X, Y), S(1)/2)&lt;/code&gt; which from my point of view doesn&amp;#8217;t require creation of a probability space object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming on to the plan for the last week, we have decided that no new PRs will be opened and focus will be towards completing the already open PRs, so that we have most of our work completed. Francesco has also suggested to test the newly introduced classes with the ones of Wolfram Alpha, so that there are no inconsistencies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_10</guid>
      <author>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807)</author>
      <title>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807): Week 10 - Debugging, testing and Haar measure</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_10/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week was about a lot of debugging and testing. I also got to know some facts about random matrices and group theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ending of 10th week, we have entered the second last week of the project. Well, this week was full of finding bugs, correcting and testing them. Mainly, I worked on, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17146"&gt;#17146&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17304"&gt;#17304&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17336"&gt;#17336&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17306"&gt;#17306&lt;/a&gt;. The first one was related to symbolic &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;, and it lacked systematic and robust tests. I pushed some commits to resolve the issue, though more is to be done. Now, coming to the second PR, it was related to circular ensembles. I got to know that distribution of these ensembles is something called Haar measure on &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;U(n)&lt;/code&gt;, group of unitary matrices. I was not familiar with this. Thanks to &lt;a href="https://github.com/jksuom"&gt;jksuom&lt;/a&gt; for sharing some papers for the same. I will go through them in the following week. The third PR fixes a bug which was found while working on circular ensembles. Acutally, &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;ask(Q.hermitian(Matrix([[2, 2 + I, 4], [2 - I, 3, I], [4, -I, 1]])))&lt;/code&gt; was giving &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;False&lt;/code&gt;, however clearly the matrix is hermitian. So, I went ahead fixing it and waiting for reviews on my approach. The last one is related to matrices with random elements and it is complete after fixing a few bugs related to canonical outputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I learnt this week? 
Well, I learnt, &lt;strong&gt;When you think your work is complete, well, sorry to say, that&amp;#8217;s the beginning ;-)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bye!!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ishanaj.wordpress.com/?p=91</guid>
      <author>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj)</author>
      <title>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj): GSoC&#x2019;19: Week-10- An alternative to the draw() function</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2019 17:58:18 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/08/05/gsoc19-week-10-an-alternative-to-the-draw-function/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This was
the end of the tenth week, and we have entered the final phase of the project.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;For the last phase we have Truss calculations to be implemented in the continuum_mechanics module. I had initiated a discussion regarding what needs to be done and how the implementation will move forward in an &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues/17302"&gt;issue #17302&lt;/a&gt;. We will have to analyse a bit more about making Truss calculations symbolic and what benefits one might get in solving it symbolically. We have some good packages to compare from like &lt;a href="https://anastruct.readthedocs.io/en/latest/?badge=latest"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. I guess a bit more discussion is needed before we go ahead with it. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Besides this, I had worked on improving the &lt;strong&gt;draw()&lt;/strong&gt; function implemented in the previous week in &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17240"&gt;PR #17240&lt;/a&gt;. I modified it to use the &lt;strong&gt;_backend&lt;/strong&gt; attribute for plotting the beam diagram. This could have worked until &lt;span id="more-91"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;I realised that using the &lt;strong&gt;_backend&lt;/strong&gt; attribute doesn&amp;#8217;t really has affect the &lt;strong&gt;Plot object. &lt;/strong&gt;To understand the last statement, lets go to how &lt;strong&gt;sympy.plot() &lt;/strong&gt;works.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;In simple terms, the equations that we pass through the &lt;strong&gt;plot()&lt;/strong&gt; function as arguments are actually stored in&lt;strong&gt; _series&lt;/strong&gt; attribute. So we can indirectly say that the basic data of the plot is stored in this attribute. But using the &lt;strong&gt;_backend &lt;/strong&gt;attribute wouldn&amp;#8217;t alter &lt;strong&gt;_series &lt;/strong&gt;at all and if &lt;strong&gt;_series &lt;/strong&gt;remains empty at the start it would end up storing nothing. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;But we are of course getting a decent plot at the end, so shouldn&amp;#8217;t we probably ignore this? No, it would surely  give the plot but we won&amp;#8217;t be getting a fully defined&lt;strong&gt; Plot &lt;/strong&gt;object which we can further use with &lt;strong&gt;PlotGrid&lt;/strong&gt; to get a subplot which includes all the five plots related to the beam.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Keeping this in mind, I tried an alternative way to directly use&lt;strong&gt; sympy.plot() &lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;to give the plot. Although a bit hard and time taking to do, I have intiated this in a draft &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17345"&gt;PR #17345&lt;/a&gt;. This PR perfectly plots a rectangular beam and loads (except point and moment loads). Only things that are left here are to plot supports and arrows denoting the direction of the load.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The example below shows how it functions: (keep in mind it just plots the basic structure of the intended beam diagram, it hasn&amp;#8217;t been completed yet)&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class="wp-block-group"&gt;&lt;div class="wp-block-group__inner-container"&gt;&lt;pre class="brush: python; collapse: false; title: ; wrap-lines: false; notranslate"&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; E, I = symbols('E, I')
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b = Beam(9, E, I)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.apply_load(-12, 9, -1)  # gets skipped
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.apply_load(50, 5, -2)  # gets skipped
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.apply_load(3, 6, 1, end=8)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.apply_load(4, 0, 0, end=5)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.draw()
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"&gt;&lt;img alt="" class="wp-image-92" height="351" src="https://ishanaj.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/screenshot-05-08-2019-19_49_21.png" width="449" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I also tried to complete the leftover PR&amp;#8217;s in this week, but still some work is left.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next week:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Completing the &lt;strong&gt;draw() &lt;/strong&gt;function&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Documentation and testing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Starting Truss implementations&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Will keep you updated!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ishanaj.wordpress.com/?p=74</guid>
      <author>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj)</author>
      <title>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj): GSoC&#x2019;19: Week-9- Analyzing the draw() function</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 05:43:20 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/07/29/gsoc19-week-9-analyzing-the-draw-function/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the
end of this week the third phase officially ends. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;There has been some discussions in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17240"&gt;PR #17240&lt;/a&gt; which implements the &lt;strong&gt;draw() &lt;/strong&gt;function. We might change the name of the function to &lt;strong&gt;plot() &lt;/strong&gt;which is more consistent with the previous beam methods &lt;strong&gt;plot_shear_force()&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;plot_bending_moment(), &lt;/strong&gt;etc.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Another discussion was about making this beam diagram a part of the &lt;strong&gt;plot_loading_results(), &lt;/strong&gt;which basically intends to plot all the beam related plots. Although currently the beam diagram uses &lt;strong&gt;matplotlib &lt;/strong&gt;as an external module, whereas the &lt;strong&gt;plot_loading_results()&lt;/strong&gt; uses &lt;strong&gt;PlotGrid&lt;/strong&gt; which is Sympy&amp;#8217;s internal functionality. So it would be a bit tricky to merge those two.&lt;span id="more-74"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We also discussed the idea or rather the possibility of directly making use of SymPy&amp;#8217;s own plot to create a beam diagram. SymPy&amp;#8217;s &lt;strong&gt;plot() &lt;/strong&gt;is capable to plotting Singularity functions, so the load applied on the beam can also be plotted using &lt;strong&gt;sympy.plot() &lt;/strong&gt;as beam.load is indeed in terms of singularity function. But there is a problem when it comes to point loads and moment loads as the are in terms singularity function of negative order (or exponent). Not sure whether the sympy plot for singularity functions of negative order is plotted correctly, but the current plot won&amp;#8217;t help us in drawing point loads and moment loads. We might have to deal with it separately.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I have
opened a discussion in the &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!topic/sympy/gmBNI-sffls"&gt;mailing
list&lt;/a&gt; regarding whether the plot is correct for singularity functions of negative
order, or what else should be done in order to get it corrected.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Also, it will be difficult to plot a rectangle (for making beam) and markers (for making supports) via sympy.plot(). One idea is to go with the &lt;strong&gt;_backend&lt;/strong&gt; attribute of sympy.plot() which helps in directly using the &lt;strong&gt;backend &lt;/strong&gt;(i.e. matplotlib backend). I will have a look over it.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Of
course if the beam diagram is made using SymPy&amp;#8217;s own plot it would surely be
preferred but for that we also need work on &lt;strong&gt;sympy.plot()&lt;/strong&gt; as currently it is limited to certain functionalities.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;From the
next week I will be starting with the last phase of implementing a Truss structure
and its respective calculations.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Since only last few weeks are left, I think I will be able to make a draft PR for the last phase implementation by the end of the next week. And then we would only be left with minor things and leftovers of the previous phases.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Also, I am glad to share that I was able to pass the second evaluations. So once again thank you mentors for all your support and guidance!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next Week:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Starting phase-IV&amp;nbsp; implementations&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Simultaneously working and discussing previous
PR&amp;#8217;s.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Will
keep you updated!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_9</guid>
      <author>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807)</author>
      <title>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807): Week 9 - Lots of reviews</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_9/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week I recieved a lot of reviews from the members of community on my various PRs and this has formed the base of the work for the next week. Let me share some of those reviews with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I told you that the PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17146"&gt;#17146&lt;/a&gt; was pending for reviews. Well, I received a lot of comments from &lt;a href="https://github.com/oscarbenjamin"&gt;@oscarbenjamin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/smichr"&gt;@smichr&lt;/a&gt; on pretty printing of symbolic &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;, the way tests are written, about &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;inf&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sup&lt;/code&gt; of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;. This in turn helped me to discover bugs in other features of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;, like, &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;reversed&lt;/code&gt;. In the following week, I will work on this stuff and will correct the things. Now moving on to the random matrices, i.e., the PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17174"&gt;#17174&lt;/a&gt; has been merged but more work is to be done for &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Matrix&lt;/code&gt; with entries as random variables. In fact, I studied about expressions of random matrices and summarised the results &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17174#issuecomment-514985333"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Though the findings suggest specific algorithms for specific expressions like sum. I am still looking for a more generalized technique and will update you if found any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, coming to the learning aspect. This week I learnt about the importance of exhaustive and systematic tests. The tests which I wrote for symbolic &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt; aren&amp;#8217;t so systematic and robust. I have found a way to improve them from &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17146#discussion_r307971324"&gt;this comment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s all for now, signing off!!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ishanaj.wordpress.com/?p=60</guid>
      <author>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj)</author>
      <title>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj): GSoC&#x2019;19: Week-8- The draw() function in action</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 04:50:39 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/07/22/gsoc19-week-8-the-draw-function-in-action/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 8&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; week has ended and we are now in the middle of phase &amp;#8211;III.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Last week was a bit of research-based, understanding &lt;strong&gt;matplotlib &lt;/strong&gt;and how it can be used to plot a beam diagram. I had a conversation with Jason Moore and Jashan where Jason shared a link of a &lt;a href="https://github.com/alfredocarella/simplebendingpractice"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;, which also was a bit of help as I took some hints from it for the &lt;strong&gt;draw() &lt;/strong&gt;function. After a lot of investigation and analysis, I was finally able to make a draft &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17240"&gt;PR # 17240&lt;/a&gt; which did the work as we intended.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of how it would function:&lt;span id="more-60"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="brush: python; collapse: false; title: ; wrap-lines: false; notranslate"&gt;

# This example has no prior logic involved. It just tests whether every functionality works or not

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; E, I = symbols('E, I')

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1 = Beam(50, E, I)

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_load(-10, 0, -1)

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_load(R1, 10, -1)

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_load(R2, 30, -1)

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_load(9, 5, 0, 23)

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_load(9, 30, 1, 50)

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_support(50, "pin")

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_support(0, "fixed")

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.apply_support(20, "roller")

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b1.draw()

&lt;/pre&gt;



&lt;figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized .single-blog-image {display: none; }"&gt;&lt;img alt="" class="wp-image-62" height="387" src="https://ishanaj.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/61594696-552b5900-ac0c-11e9-96f9-4ba257dbf92c-1.png" width="467" /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Here we are using &lt;strong&gt;matplotlib&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;numpy&lt;/strong&gt; by importing them as external modules. Of course, it would be better to have it done via &lt;strong&gt;SymPy&amp;#8217;s&lt;/strong&gt; own &lt;strong&gt;plot()&lt;/strong&gt;, but I think that is something we could work on in later stages as&lt;strong&gt; SymPy&amp;#8217;s plot()&lt;/strong&gt; is limited to work on equations and stuff (although on can use &lt;strong&gt;_backend &lt;/strong&gt;attribute for further functionalities). &amp;nbsp;Also to be noted here that &lt;strong&gt;SymPy&amp;#8217;s plot()&lt;/strong&gt; is not a replica of &lt;strong&gt;matplotib&amp;#8217;s plot()&lt;/strong&gt; but it makes it easier for SymPy equation to be plotted and it uses&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;matplotlib&lt;/strong&gt; to do so.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Following are the&lt;strong&gt; m&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;atplotlib&lt;/strong&gt; modules/classes used:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org/api/_as_gen/matplotlib.patches.Rectangle.html"&gt;matplotlib.patches.Rectangle&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;-to draw the beam&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org/api/_as_gen/matplotlib.pyplot.annotate.html"&gt;matplotlib.pyplot.annotate&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8211; to draw arrows of load&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org/3.1.1/api/markers_api.html"&gt;matplotlib.markers&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8211; to draw supports&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Also, considering Jason&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17240#issuecomment-513577696"&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt; in the PR, I will have to work on making &lt;strong&gt;SymPy&amp;#8217;s plot()&lt;/strong&gt; to accept a singularity function, so that it would be easier to plot &lt;strong&gt;loads &lt;/strong&gt;which are indeed equations of Singularity function. This is still in consideration, so I will have to look into it and of course will have a discussion on how it is to be done.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Currently, I am not able to determine how to plot parabolic loads. I think this could be added later as we should currently focus on plotting simple parts and certainly work on other complexities later. But we can have a discussion on it.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Other PR&amp;#8217;s are still being parallelly worked on.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next Week:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Working on the idea of plotting singularity function via SymPy&amp;#8217;s plot()&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Plotting parabolic loads&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Writing documentation and tests&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Will keep you updated!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_8</guid>
      <author>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807)</author>
      <title>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807): Week 8 - Heading towards completion</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_8/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the 8th week, the second phase of my project is complete and we are heading towards the end of GSoC 2019. 
This blog post summarises the work done between phase 1 and phase 3, in terms of PRs. Moreover, I will share with you my plans for the last phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked on the following PRs(listed in chronological order) during the second phase, some of them got merged and few are open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Merged&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16934"&gt;#16934&lt;/a&gt; : The bug fixes were complete and the further work has been handed over to my co-student, Ritesh.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16962"&gt;#16962&lt;/a&gt; : This was continuation of the work done in phase 1 for allowing symbolic dimensions in finite random variables. As I planned, this PR got merged in phase 2, after some changes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17083"&gt;#17083&lt;/a&gt;: The work done in this PR framed the platform and reason for the next one. The algorithm that got merged was a bit difficult to extend, and maintain. Thanks to Francesco for his &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17083#issuecomment-508256359"&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt; for motivating me to re-think the whole framework.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17163"&gt;#17163&lt;/a&gt; : This was one of the most challenging PRs of the project till now, because, it involved re-designing the algorithm, refactoring the code and moreover lot of thinking. The details can be found at &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17163#issuecomment-510939984"&gt;this comment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17174"&gt;#17174&lt;/a&gt; : This PR aims at adding random matrices to sympy. Currently, I am studying about the expressions involving random matrices and computing their densities.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17146"&gt;#17146&lt;/a&gt; : This PR aims at allowing symbolic parameters to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;. The work is complete and I am waiting for final reviews. Hopefully it gets merged.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the above PRs I also reviewed code written by other contributors.
Overall, according to me phase 2 was a great learning and logical experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me share with you the outline of my plan for phase 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outline is given below,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will work on enhancing the result generation by the stats module as was planned in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The work on random matrices will be extended and I will add more features to them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Probably, if time permits, I will try to do some more refactoring of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats.frv&lt;/code&gt;, and will try to add some more stochastic processes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will also try to merge my open PRs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading and see you soon in phase 3. Bye!!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ishanaj.wordpress.com/?p=58</guid>
      <author>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj)</author>
      <title>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj): GSoC&#x2019;19: Week-7- Starting with the phase-III draw() function</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 03:02:10 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/07/15/gsoc19-week-7-starting-with-the-phase-iii-draw-function/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The week was successfully completed as planned. The work on &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17122"&gt;Column class&lt;/a&gt; has been completed.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The documentation and tests have been written and with some changes in the &lt;strong&gt;solve_slope_deflection()&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;critical_load(),&lt;/strong&gt; the &lt;strong&gt;Column&lt;/strong&gt; class is now able to handle cases with trivial solutions of the constants ( C1 &amp;amp; C2) which made the deflection equation zero.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, another problem that we had with the &lt;strong&gt;pinned-fixed&lt;/strong&gt; end condition, where &lt;strong&gt;solve()&lt;/strong&gt; wasn&amp;#8217;t giving the output in the required form, has temporary been handled by making an &lt;strong&gt;XFAIL &lt;/strong&gt;test against it. We can work on it later. Either there has to be some changes in &lt;strong&gt;solve()&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;so that we would be able to handle our case or we might have to figure out a way to rewrite it into the desired form.&lt;span id="more-58"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;With the end of this week,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17122"&gt;PR #17122&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17153"&gt;PR #17153&lt;/a&gt; are complete and ready for review. I have made some changes addressing some of the reviews, and we can have further discussions on it.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Now, also moving on to the next phase, I have done a bit of research on it. I will most probably open a discussion to have an initial discussion regarding how work will progress in this stage. This phase is regarding plotting the beam diagrams using &lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org/"&gt;matplotlib&lt;/a&gt;. I have also considered &lt;strong&gt;pyglet&lt;/strong&gt; plotting module of SymPy, which according to the &lt;a href="https://docs.sympy.org/latest/modules/plotting.html#plotting-geometric-entities"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; is capable of plotting geometries, but there has been some problems in this module and it doesn&amp;#8217;t seem to be working well. I had earlier made an &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues/16537"&gt;issue #16537&lt;/a&gt; regarding the same, but there seems to be no improvement here.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;So, we will be discussing the rest in an issue-cum-discussion, in the upcoming week.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next week:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Working on the Stage-III&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Simultaneously, discussing the leftover PR&amp;#8217;s and trying to finish them and make a merge.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Most probably, on successful discussion and planning, I will be opening a draft work-in-progress PR for the &lt;strong&gt;draw()&lt;/strong&gt; function in stage &amp;#8211;III.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Will keep you updated!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_7</guid>
      <author>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807)</author>
      <title>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807): Week 7 - All about logics and algorithms</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_7/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week required a lot of thinking before jumping to code the stuff. Interested? Okay move on to next paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I worked on three PRs, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17163"&gt;#17163&lt;/a&gt; for continuous time Markov chains, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17174"&gt;#17174&lt;/a&gt; for random matrices and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17146"&gt;#17146&lt;/a&gt; for symbolic Ranges. The first and the last PRs are very much intensive. I developed a new algorithm for the query handler of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;ContinuousMarkovChain.probability&lt;/code&gt; method, because the previous one which I implemented in &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;DiscreteMarkovChain.probability&lt;/code&gt;, was not easy to maintain, quite ad-hoc, rigid and difficult to extend. The philosophy behind the algorithm is recursion i.e., boil everything down to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Relational&lt;/code&gt; query, convert them to sets and then calculate the probability. You can find the complete description &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17163#issuecomment-510939984"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I am waiting for any critical objections from my mentors and after that I will refactor the code as suggested by &lt;a href="https://github.com/oscarbenjamin"&gt;oscarbenjamin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/jksuom"&gt;jksuom&lt;/a&gt;. So, now let&amp;#8217;s move on to random matrices. As it was to be implemented from scratch, it required a bit of thinking to reach a decent architecture. Currently, the PR is at a basic level, and some more testing is to be done. Now, coming on to symbolic &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;. Let me tell you, it requires a lot of logical thinking to make &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt; accept symbolic parameters. A lot of tests fail, and a lot of debugging has to be done to make a method work. In fact, we might deprecate &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;xrange&lt;/code&gt; support from &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt; because we are going to drop &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Python 2&lt;/code&gt; support from &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;SymPy&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I learnt to combine the concepts from algorithms and software engineering to develop the stuff I mentioned above. This was the best week of my overall GSoC experience till now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot more lies ahead. Bye!!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ishanaj.wordpress.com/?p=56</guid>
      <author>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj)</author>
      <title>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj): GSoC&#x2019;19: Week-6-Completing the Column class.</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2019 04:44:15 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/07/08/gsoc19-week-6-completing-the-column-class/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The sixth week has ended with a lot of work to be done ahead.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Last week the work was majorly focused on the work in progress &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17122"&gt;PR #17122&lt;/a&gt;. I have included the critical load function which makes the Column class capable of determining the critical load. Some problems still came up in solving some equations. I have made an &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues/17162"&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt; related to those.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;An equation similar to &lt;strong&gt;tan(x) &amp;#8211; x&lt;/strong&gt; comes up while determining the critical load for the&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;pinned-fixed&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;end-condition. SymPy&amp;#8217;s &lt;strong&gt;solve() &lt;/strong&gt;won&amp;#8217;t be able to solve such an equation, and as per the solution given in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues/17162"&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt;, I think that &lt;strong&gt;nsolve()&lt;/strong&gt; would surely help in this case. So I will be going ahead to solve it using the approximation returned by &lt;strong&gt;nsolve()&lt;/strong&gt; to handle this condition.&lt;span id="more-56"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Another problem that I faced was determining deflection and critical load for the&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;pinned-pinned&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;end-condition. Here, the deflection comes out to be:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C1*sin(sqrt(P)*x/(sqrt(E)*sqrt(I)))&lt;/strong&gt; +&lt;strong&gt; C2*cos(sqrt(P)*x/(sqrt(E)*sqrt(I)))&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Now on solving it for constants &lt;strong&gt;C1&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;C2, &lt;/strong&gt;using initial boundary conditions,&amp;nbsp;both come out to be &lt;strong&gt;0&lt;/strong&gt;, making the deflection &lt;strong&gt;zero&lt;/strong&gt;. This implies that no buckling occurs, which is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Even when solving it manually, this situation occurs, we deal with it by putting &lt;strong&gt;C2 = 0 &lt;/strong&gt;and instead of putting &lt;strong&gt;C1 = 0,&lt;/strong&gt; we consider the &lt;strong&gt;sin &lt;/strong&gt;term equal to zero and then solve for &lt;strong&gt;P (critical load).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;So, I will be adding a few more lines of code to deal with this situation.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Apart from working on this module, I have also opened another &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17153"&gt;PR #17153&lt;/a&gt; which implement methods&amp;nbsp;to determine &lt;strong&gt;section modulus&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;polar modulus&lt;/strong&gt; of any polygon (more precisely a cross-section). Initially it was a draft PR, but now the work has been completed on it. Once I get the approval, I will also be adding the same for the Ellipses module. Also, if &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17001"&gt;cut_section()&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;gets successfully implemented I will be adding another method to determine the first moment.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure the work on &lt;strong&gt;Column class&lt;/strong&gt; will be successfully completed before the end of the next week. Also, we will be heading towards the next stage which intends to plot beam diagrams using matplotlib. Till then we can have an initial discussion regarding the same.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next Week:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Improving the &lt;strong&gt;critical_load()&lt;/strong&gt; to handle the above problems&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Completing the Column class (documentation and tests)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Starting with the next phase&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Will keep you updated!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_6</guid>
      <author>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807)</author>
      <title>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807): Week 6 - Some extensions</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_6/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week was a mix of discussion on design and extending previous work. I also got to know about some new cool features of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;SymPy&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the plan proposed in &lt;a href="https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_4/"&gt;Week 4&lt;/a&gt;, I have completed my work on &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;DiscreteMarkovChain&lt;/code&gt; via &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17083"&gt;PR #17083&lt;/a&gt;. I used the &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;as_set&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;as_relational&lt;/code&gt; methods which helped me to cover many miscellaneous cases and probably, now &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;DiscreteMarkovChain&lt;/code&gt; is quite dynamic and can handle various generic &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;probability&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;expectation&lt;/code&gt; queries. I have also started the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17163"&gt;PR #17163&lt;/a&gt; for adding &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;ContinuousMarkovChain&lt;/code&gt; and I am observing that it&amp;#8217;s a bit tricky to maintain both the performance and result quality while working on it. Now, moving on to symbolic &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;,well, the work has been started in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17146"&gt;PR #17146&lt;/a&gt; and I have figured out one disparity between &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt; and python&amp;#8217;s &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;range&lt;/code&gt;(details available at &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17146#discussion_r300162219"&gt;this thread&lt;/a&gt;). I will try to fix it by making minimal changes to the code. The tensorflow related &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17103"&gt;PR #17103&lt;/a&gt; which I started in the previous week is also almost complete and is waiting for &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Tensorflow 2.0&lt;/code&gt; release. I am also studying a bit about the architecture of the above framework to make changes to &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;lambdify&lt;/code&gt;. Regarding random matrices, I believe that discussion has reached its final stages and I am waiting for the comments from Francesco for improvements at the issue &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues/17039"&gt;#17039&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me share with you about my discoveries and learnings in this week. Well, thanks to Francesco for telling me about, &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.multipledispatch&lt;/code&gt;. It helps in implementing operator overloading like in C/C++. I liked it very much. I also read about continuous Markov chain and discovered about generator matrix, forward and backward equations. Adding one interesting fact, that Poisson process and continuous Markov chain are very closely related via generator matrices it will make the implementation of the former much easier :D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving you for now, Bye!!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_5</guid>
      <author>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807)</author>
      <title>Gagandeep Singh (czgdp1807): Week 5 - Transition towards Phase 2</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://czgdp1807.github.io/week_5/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The evaluation results for phase 1 are out, and I am very glad to share with you that I have passed with flying colors. I received, &amp;#8220;Well done so far.&amp;#8221; as the feedback for my work till now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now let us move to the work done in the gap between phase 1 and phase 2. Firstly, both of my open PRs of the previous phase, i.e., &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16962"&gt;#16962&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16934"&gt;#16934&lt;/a&gt; have been merged. Though for symbolic dimensions some more work has to be done to make &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;sympy.stats.frv&lt;/code&gt; more efficient and maintainable. I have also started my work, PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17083"&gt;#17083&lt;/a&gt;, to extend the scope of queries for &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;DiscreteMarkovChain&lt;/code&gt; and the system has become a bit smarter. In fact, during this week, while working on the PR, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17103"&gt;#17103&lt;/a&gt;, I came across the news that Tensorflow has changed a lot of APIs  while migrating from 1.x to 2.x. AFAIK, they are moving towards &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Function&lt;/code&gt; approach from the previous &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;Session&lt;/code&gt; approach, and due to that, SymPy&amp;#8217;s &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;lambdify&lt;/code&gt; faced some issues which I will be fixing soon with the help of other members. The Tensorflow details can be seen &lt;a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/community/blob/b1d83bf2ee3fc72650140b89656e29932db36226/rfcs/20180918-functions-not-sessions-20.md"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let&amp;#8217;s move to the learning part. During the transition period I learnt about the dependencies of &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;SymPy&lt;/code&gt;. Moreover, I came across, how, some bugs can be unnoticed when left untested. Thanks again to &lt;a href="https://github.com/oscarbenjamin"&gt;oscarbenjamin&lt;/a&gt; for letting me know about the bugs related to variance of finite random variables. I also got to know that, how bare &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;except&lt;/code&gt; can even catch keyboard interrupt and that&amp;#8217;s what makes it quite vulnerable. Thanks to &lt;a href="https://github.com/sidhantnagpal"&gt;sidhantnagpal&lt;/a&gt; for helping me with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that&amp;#8217;s all for this, see you next week. Bye!!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ishanaj.wordpress.com/?p=54</guid>
      <author>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj)</author>
      <title>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj): GSoC&#x2019;19: Week-5 &#x2013; Moving on with a Non-mutable Column class</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 18:52:29 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/07/01/gsoc19-week-5-moving-on-with-a-non-mutable-column-class/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A lot of things happened this week and I am happy to inform you that &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17055"&gt;PR #17055&lt;/a&gt; has been successfully merged. The beam module now supports the cross-sectional shape of the beam as an alternative parameter to the second moment. With this, the aim of the stage-I to integrate the geometry module with beam module has been accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Although we need to add some examples in the docs, to make it easier for the user to understand how to use this new feature.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Coming on to stage-II, I had already, initiated a &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues/17072"&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; to finalize the API of the new Column class that is to be implemented as a part of the continuum mechanics module in this stage.&lt;span id="more-54"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We concluded that it would be much better if the Column class remains non-mutable i.e. unlike the beam class where a beam is formed in a piecewise form, the new Column class would take all its required input data during the declaration and then one can call different methods to calculate different things.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I have made a &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17122"&gt;work-in-progress PR #17122&lt;/a&gt; implementing the Column class which performs the required buckling calculations. Currently, I have not included a method to calculate the critical load as there was a bit of problem with the form of the equation which the &lt;strong&gt;dsolve() &lt;/strong&gt;returns after solving the differential equation of buckling. &lt;a href="https://docs.sympy.org/latest/modules/solvers/ode.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dsolve(&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; is SymPy&amp;#8217;s differential equation solver.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;In general, if we solve the general equation of buckling manually, we might apply the &lt;strong&gt;method of undetermined coefficients&lt;/strong&gt;, which of course even &lt;strong&gt;dsolve() &lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;is capable to apply, but it gives the answer in an exponent form, while we need it in a trigonometric form (for ease of further calculations). So after seeking different methods trying to convert this equation in terms of &lt;strong&gt;sin(x)&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;cos(x), &lt;/strong&gt;I finally had to put that problem in the discussion, where Oscar Benjamin, gave an idea to declare the variables as positive in order to get it in terms of &lt;strong&gt;sin &lt;/strong&gt;and&lt;strong&gt; cos.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;I tried that it works well for our case. I will have to figure out the further calculation of the critical load.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Hopefully will be updating the code with a new method to calculate critical load, soon.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Also, I have planned to have a method to solve the &lt;strong&gt;unknown reactions&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;reaction moments&lt;/strong&gt;, which would use the &lt;strong&gt;boundary conditions&lt;/strong&gt; to get their values.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;With all these things going on, this week we also had our first evaluations, and I am very happy to say that I have passed it. &lt;strong&gt;Thanks to the mentors!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next Week:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Completing Column class with all its methods&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Adding tests and documentation.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Starting discussions for the next stage.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I will try to finish working on the Column class this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Will keep you updated!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ishanaj.wordpress.com/?p=52</guid>
      <author>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj)</author>
      <title>Ishan Joshi (ishanaj): GSoC&#x2019;19: Week-4-Starting with Column Buckling implementation</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 18:41:36 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://ishanaj.wordpress.com/2019/06/24/gsoc19-week-4-starting-with-column-buckling-implementation/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finalizing what had been discussed in &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/16964"&gt;PR #16964&lt;/a&gt; for integrating geometry module with the beam module,&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/17055"&gt; PR #17055&lt;/a&gt; was opened which is now ready to go!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;There is no special function for defining the cross-section of a Beam object. A user can simply pass the geometry object as a parameter instead of the &lt;strong&gt;second_moment, &lt;/strong&gt;and the corresponding second moment would be calculated internally. The example below might explain this better:&lt;span id="more-52"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="brush: python; collapse: false; title: ; wrap-lines: false; notranslate"&gt;

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b = Beam(l, E, Circle((0, 0), r))

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.second_moment

pi*r*Abs(r)**3/4

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.cross_section

Circle(Point2D(0, 0), r)

&lt;/pre&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Further, the &lt;strong&gt;cross_section&lt;/strong&gt; attribute can be changed even after the beam is created. Every time the &lt;strong&gt;cross_section&lt;/strong&gt; is assigned a new value, the &lt;strong&gt;second_moment&lt;/strong&gt; gets automatically updated.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Similarly, every time the user changes the &lt;strong&gt;second_moment&lt;/strong&gt; explicitly after the creation of the beam, the previous &lt;strong&gt;cross_section&lt;/strong&gt; gets destroyed, or in other words, the &lt;strong&gt;cross_section&lt;/strong&gt; is set to None.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="brush: python; collapse: false; title: ; wrap-lines: false; notranslate"&gt;

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b = Beam(l, E, Circle((0, 0), r))

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; I&amp;#160; = Symbol(&amp;#8216;I&amp;#8217;)

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.second_moment = I

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.cross_section

None

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.second_moment = Polygon((0, 0), (a, 0), (a, b), (0, b))

ValueError: To update cross-section geometry use `cross_section` attribute

&lt;/pre&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The PR is complete and just needs the final approval from the mentors.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, I had worked on the column buckling calculations which is a part of the stage &amp;#8211;II.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I have opened an &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues/17072"&gt;issue-cum-discussion&lt;/a&gt; for discussing its API and further implementations.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Since the calculations of the Column Buckling are very much different from those of beam bending, we will have to make a separate class Column. The basic API and the way the calculations are supposed to go can be seen from the stage &amp;#8211;II in the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1LOtMTr9cCrzQ8_OnKrgkZs8wFS9N9PxlR10h3aKG0jg/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I would be making a PR for column buckling calculations within a day or two, once some initial questions (as mentioned in the issue-cum-discussion) gets clarified.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;Next Week:&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Finalizing the basic API and implementations of Column class&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Making a PR for the above implementations&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Documentation and testing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Will keep you updated!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://gxyd.github.io/blogs/DL-for-NLP</guid>
      <author>Gaurav Dhingra (gxyd)</author>
      <title>Gaurav Dhingra (gxyd): Deep learning for Natural Language Processing learnings 1</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://gxyd.github.io/blogs/DL-for-NLP/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Conclusion of things done on weekend regarding learning &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;word2vec&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;word2vec&lt;/code&gt; is one of the really good ways to solve the problem of &amp;#8220;word-embedding&amp;#8221;.
  , developed by researchers at google (Tomas Mikolov and colleagues)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;GloVe&lt;/code&gt; (Global Vectors for Word Representation) is another really good way to compute
  word embeddings, developed at Stanford.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The original research papers (by Tomas Mikolov and colleagues) on word2vec
  [1]. Efficient Estimation of Word Representation in Vector Spaces
  [2]. Distributed Representation of words and phrases and their composotionality&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;these two papers on reading sucked the hell out of me (probably because I don&amp;#8217;t
  have much background in Neural networks).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Rather I found myself having to go through the paper
  [3]. word2vec explained: Deriving Mikolo et al&amp;#8217;s negative sampling word embedding
      method&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;d a go through the lecture 7 (skipped the lectures 4, 5 and 6), to get an idea
  of what are deep learning frameworks like Tensorflow (lecuture 7 is an introduction to it).
  It gives a basic idea of why to use Tensorflow and performing basic operations with
  it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All in all this weekend was all focused on things related to NLP stuff. I am hopeful
  that in the next year I might be able to take a few more step towards learning
  the NLP stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://nkhlpappu.wordpress.com/?p=17</guid>
      <author>Nikhil Pappu (NikhilPappu)</author>
      <title>Nikhil Pappu (NikhilPappu): GSoC 2018: Autolev Parser (using ANTLRv4): Final Report</title>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Aug 2018 21:28:45 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://nkhlpappu.wordpress.com/2018/08/11/gsoc-2018-autolev-parser-using-antlrv4-final-report/</link>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;About Me:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am Nikhil Pappu, an undergraduate Computer Science student at the International Institute of Information Technology, Bangalore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About the Project:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autolev (now superseded by MotionGenesis) is a domain specific language used for symbolic multibody dynamics. The SymPy mechanics module now has enough power and functionality to be a fully featured symbolic dynamics module. The parser parses Autolev (version 4.1) code to SymPy code by making use of SymPy&amp;#8217;s math libraries and the mechanics module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parser has been built using the &lt;a href="http://www.antlr.org/"&gt;ANTLR&lt;/a&gt; framework and its main purpose is to help former users of Autolev to get familiarized with multibody dynamics in SymPy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Plan:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan was to build a parser using ANTLR that could parse Autolev code to SymPy code.&amp;#160; Overall,&amp;#160; I think I was able to achieve most of what I had hoped for. I had faced some difficulties in some areas of the parser due to the very different nature of Autolev and Python. The parser has some issues as a result. I have specified all the details in the documentation I have written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Work Done:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a parser for the Autolev language which is now a part of SymPy in the parsing module. I have written the code for the parser using the ANTLR framework. I have also included a bunch of tests for testing the rules of the parser code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of the work was a part of PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14758"&gt;#14758&lt;/a&gt;. I made a second PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15006"&gt;#15006&lt;/a&gt; for the changes I had made after the main PR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have written documentation for the parser which is a part of these PRs: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15046"&gt;#15046&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15066"&gt;#15066&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15067"&gt;#15067&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also written a PyDy for Autolev Users guide which is a part of PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15077"&gt;#15077&lt;/a&gt;. This guide is meant to be a quick reference for looking up Autolev-PyDy equivalents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Future Work:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The parser has been built by referring to and parsing codes from the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://web.mae.ufl.edu/~fregly/PDFs/autolev_tutorial.pdf"&gt;Autolev Tutorial&lt;/a&gt; and the book &lt;em&gt;Dynamics Online: Theory and Implementation Using Autolev&lt;/em&gt;. Basically, the process involved going through each of these codes, validating the parser results and improving the rules if required to make sure the codes parsed well.
&lt;p&gt;As of now, a large number of codes of &lt;em&gt;Dynamics Online&lt;/em&gt; have been parsed. Completing all the remaining codes of the book would make the parser more complete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are some limitations and issues with the parser and these have been discussed in the documentation. The plan is to fix these in order of priority.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The parser is currently built using a kind of Concrete Syntax Tree (CST) using the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.antlr.org/"&gt;ANTLR&lt;/a&gt; framework. It would be ideal to switch from a CST to an Abstract Syntax Tree (AST). This way, the parser code will be independent of the ANTLR grammar which makes it a lot more flexible. It would also be easier to make changes to the grammar and the rules of the parser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to keep contributing to SymPy. I would be doing a lot of math in college especially related to data science so I would love to contribute in areas like Probability and Algebra among others. I would also like to help newcomers feel comfortable with the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank my mentors &lt;a href="https://github.com/certik"&gt;Ond&amp;#345;ej &amp;#268;ert&amp;#237;k&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/moorepants"&gt;Jason Moore&lt;/a&gt; for believing in me and taking time out from their busy schedules to guide me throughout the project. I would also like to thank &lt;a href="https://github.com/asmeurer"&gt;Aaron Meurer&lt;/a&gt; for looking over GSoC as the org admin and making sure that we all had a great experience working with SymPy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Links:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Main PR: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14758"&gt;#14758&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Updated parser code PR: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15006"&gt;#15006&lt;/a&gt; and&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15013"&gt; #15013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documentation PRs: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15046"&gt;#15046&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15066"&gt;#15066&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15067"&gt;#15067&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PyDy for Autolev Users guide PR: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15077"&gt;#15077&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weekly Blog link: &lt;a href="https://nkhlpappu.wordpress.com/"&gt;https://nkhlpappu.wordpress.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://nkhlpappu.wordpress.com/?p=15</guid>
      <author>Nikhil Pappu (NikhilPappu)</author>
      <title>Nikhil Pappu (NikhilPappu): Autolev Parser: Status Update</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2018 20:36:26 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://nkhlpappu.wordpress.com/2018/08/03/autolev-parser-status-update-4/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have made some changes to the parser code to parse more files since &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14758"&gt;#14758&lt;/a&gt; has been merged. I have also made the changes suggested in that PR after it had been merged. I have opened a new PR&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15006/"&gt;#15006&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;for the updated parser code. I have also opened &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15013"&gt;#15013&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;to include tests for physics functions which I didn&amp;#8217;t do in the initial PR. The GitLab repo autolev-test-examples is in good shape now and is part of the sympy user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently writing the documentation in which I shall include how to use the parser, gotchas, limitations, issues and future improvements. I shall also include a rewritten version of the PyDy for Autolev Users guide in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shall then write the output tests (Tests to compare the outputs of Autolev against those of SymPy) for most of the test examples in the GitLab repo (I shall include these in a directory called output-tests in the GitLab repo). I think its good to put them here as I don&amp;#8217;t see the need to test these on Travis as changing the parser code won&amp;#8217;t affect these. Plus, they will be in a place where the test examples are which are what they will be based on. We could still test these on Travis if required even from here I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I shall wrap things up with the Final Report and Submission.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://singhjashan.wordpress.com/?p=95</guid>
      <author>Jashanpreet Singh Sraw (jashan498)</author>
      <title>Jashanpreet Singh Sraw (jashan498): Week 11: unset_show bug and documentation</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 17:45:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://singhjashan.wordpress.com/2018/07/30/week-11-unset_show-bug-and-documentation/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, I created&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14967"&gt;#14967&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;for implementation of plotting methods.&amp;#160;Soon after pushing my commits, many of the jobs failed on Travis. It was strange as I was not able to reciprocate the errors locally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After discussing it on Gitter, I got to know that it was due to the printing of plots using TextBackend in the doctest in absence of matplotlib. As matplotlib was present in my system,&amp;#160; doctest used matplotlib backend instead of TextBackend locally, hence passing all tests.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/jksuom"&gt;Kalevi&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;suggested using&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;unset_show &lt;/em&gt;to stop the printing of plots during doctest but apparently,&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;unset_show&amp;#160;&lt;/em&gt;didn&amp;#8217;t work for TextBackend. This was fixed by&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14984"&gt;#14984&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;later that day and&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14967"&gt;#14967&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;passed all the tests after former one was merged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I also started editing&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14453"&gt;#14453&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;for documentation. It included a few beam problems along with their ascii diagrams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next Week&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14967"&gt;#14967&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;and&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14453"&gt;#14453&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;gets merged.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#160;Add more beam problems for documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-1036447522835236737.post-5320864463564984752</guid>
      <author>Ashish Kumar Gaurav (ashishkg0022)</author>
      <title>Ashish Kumar Gaurav (ashishkg0022): GSoC 2018: Week 11</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2018 14:47:17 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>http://ashishkg0022.blogspot.com/2018/07/gsoc-2018-week-11.html</link>
      <description>&lt;div dir="ltr" style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;Hello everyone. Here is the brief progress of Rubi&amp;nbsp;module in the 11th week of GSoC period.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;The main PR, which contains the major changes of this GSoC period was merged this week. I had not run pyflakes on it. I ran pyflakes on the main PR and fixed undefined issues.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;This week was mainly spent to test code generation. Initially, there was some error in generating the code. An &lt;a href="https://github.com/HPAC/matchpy/issues/33"&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt; was opened in this regard. I tried various other structure of Rubi to get it working.&amp;nbsp; Currently, patterns are not matched correctly. I have opened a &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14988"&gt;PR&lt;/a&gt; for this. We are still trying to get the code generator working so that we can reduce the loading time of rules. Now, the loading time of all rules is around 10 minutes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://nkhlpappu.wordpress.com/?p=13</guid>
      <author>Nikhil Pappu (NikhilPappu)</author>
      <title>Nikhil Pappu (NikhilPappu): Autolev Parser: Status Update</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 20:24:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://nkhlpappu.wordpress.com/2018/07/27/autolev-parser-status-update-3/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello Everyone. I have been working on getting the PR&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14758"&gt;#14758&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;into shape and now it is finally merged. I have written my own tests for the PR so as to not include copyrighted files that belong to the creators of Autolev.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am now working on a &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/NikhilPappu/test-examples/"&gt;test-examples repo&lt;/a&gt; which serves as a showcase of the parser and also as a source of additional tests. The repo is private on GitLab as it contains copyrighted files. You can request access at the repo link above. Files from this repo can be copied over to the test_examples folder of parsing/autolev to use them as tests. From now, I will be working on adding more examples from the PyDy example repo, Autolev Tutorial, and Dynamics Online to this repo while improving the code of the parser to parse all these codes. I am also making note of things like errors, inaccuracies etc to include them in the Documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will open another PR once I have made enough number of changes to the parser code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my plan for the future of this project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Till the end of GSoC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on getting the test-examples repo in good shape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write extensive Documentation (explaining what the parser can do, how to use it,&amp;#160; limitations, issues, future improvements etc).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on as many Dynamics Online codes (which I shall include in the repo) as possible (Wrap up Ch4 and hoping to get half of Ch5 done (as it is quite big)).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post GSoC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish the rest of the Dynamics Online Book (Whatever is left of Ch5 and also Ch6 which I think is less important).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on the issues that I will be listing down in the documentation one by one after discussing the possible fixes (Some of these might require changes in the parser while some others require changes in the SymPy code while I do not have much of an idea about the fixes of some other ones).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nikhil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://singhjashan.wordpress.com/?p=93</guid>
      <author>Jashanpreet Singh Sraw (jashan498)</author>
      <title>Jashanpreet Singh Sraw (jashan498): Week 10: Implementing plotting methods</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2018 18:12:09 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://singhjashan.wordpress.com/2018/07/24/week-10-implementing-plotting-methods/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week I started working on implementing methods to plot Shear force, bending moment, slope and deflection diagrams.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14967"&gt;#14967&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;was created for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mainly four methods were added to the Beam class:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;plot_shear_force: This method returns a plot for Shear force present in the Beam object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;plot_bending_moment: This method returns a plot for Bending moment present in the Beam object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;plot_slope: This method returns a plot for slope of the elastic curve of the Beam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;plot_delfection: This method returns a plot for the deflection curve of the Beam object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;plot_loading_results: This method returns&amp;#160;fig object containing subplots of Shear Force, Bending Moment,&amp;#160;Slope and Deflection of the Beam object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/jashan498/beam_examples/blob/master/beam_plots.ipynb"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;is a sample notebook demonstrating how to use these plotting methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next Week&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14967"&gt;#14967&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;gets merged.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add more beam problems to the documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-1036447522835236737.post-4503634706614858581</guid>
      <author>Ashish Kumar Gaurav (ashishkg0022)</author>
      <title>Ashish Kumar Gaurav (ashishkg0022): GSoC 2018: Week 10</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 15:35:32 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>http://ashishkg0022.blogspot.com/2018/07/gsoc-2018-week-10.html</link>
      <description>&lt;div dir="ltr" style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;Hello everyone. Here is the brief progress of Rubi&amp;nbsp;module in the 10th week of GSoC period.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;Last week, we were able to load all rules. Rubi has now come in a very stable and working condition. One Missing thing in the main &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14756"&gt;PR&lt;/a&gt; was missing instructions and documentation. This week I tried my best to write instructions, so that a new user can easily get familiar with it. I have kept it really simple.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;Initially, I wrote a script in Mathematica to generate downvalues&amp;nbsp;in separate files. This was done till now manually, but now it's automated. Then I wrote a sympy&amp;nbsp;script to generate all rules and constraints in proper files directly just by running a function.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;For a more easier understanding of steps, I created&amp;nbsp;`rubi_parsing_guide.md` explaining all steps.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;Next thing I realised that it would be good if we create a parsing script for the tests too. Till now I used maple format. But a lot of manual things were required. So I wrote a script which directly parses tests into sympy&amp;nbsp;format. All this are added properly in `rubi_parsing_guide.md`.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;`init` in Rubi&amp;nbsp;too was updated with proper explanation of basic structure of rules and constraints. I also updated docs of few important utility_functions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;Now a new user can easily get familiar with Rubi and working with it will be simple.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt;I have also opened a new &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14956"&gt;PR&lt;/a&gt; for new utility_functions. Once the old &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14756"&gt;PR&lt;/a&gt; gets merged, we can merge this.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://nkhlpappu.wordpress.com/?p=9</guid>
      <author>Nikhil Pappu (NikhilPappu)</author>
      <title>Nikhil Pappu (NikhilPappu): Autolev Parser: Status Update</title>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jul 2018 22:31:06 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://nkhlpappu.wordpress.com/2018/07/20/autolev-parser-status-update-2/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been working on improving the parser by parsing Dynamics online codes, planning out how to go about writing tests and other aspects of the project and getting the PR into shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently working on writing tests to cover all the rules of the parser. I should be done with this in 2 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the plan I have for the third phase:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Make the PR merge ready:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Finish the tests for the parser rules and get the PR merged.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;open a new PR to work on further improvements.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;additional_tests (will be added in a private BitBucket repo). Here I shall go through many codes from these sources and improve the parser to parse most of these. I shall take notes on little details and errors so that I can include them in the documentation.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyDy example repo (mass spring damper, double pendulum, chaos pendulum examples)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Dynamics Online Chapters 1 &amp;#8211; 4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Autolev Tutorial Examples (5.1 &amp;#8211; 5.7)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Documentation (What the parser can do, How it should be used, Limitations, Future improvements etc)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the parser parse Dynamics Online Chapter 5 codes and the Bicycle Model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Final Report&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://singhjashan.wordpress.com/?p=71</guid>
      <author>Jashanpreet Singh Sraw (jashan498)</author>
      <title>Jashanpreet Singh Sraw (jashan498): Week 8 &amp; 9: Beam_3d class</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 16:42:54 GMT</pubDate>
      <link>https://singhjashan.wordpress.com/2018/07/17/week-8-9-07-july-20-july/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I started implementing Beam_3d class which can be used to find Shear force, Bending moment, Slope, Deflection and other few things for the Beam object.&amp;#160; PR&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14883"&gt;#14883&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;was created for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I implemented Beam_3d class using&amp;#160;&amp;#160;&lt;a href="http://homes.civil.aau.dk/jc/FemteSemester/Beams3D.pdf" rel="nofollow"&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;as a reference. Actually, like Beam class, it uses a few sets of equations to find certain quantities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To find&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;Shear force&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#160;and&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;Bending moment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/31389737/42560335-0c45e50e-8514-11e8-9fb1-f9d27040b4d8.png" rel="noopener"&gt;&lt;img alt="shear" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/31389737/42560335-0c45e50e-8514-11e8-9fb1-f9d27040b4d8.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
where&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;[N, Q&lt;sub&gt;y&lt;/sub&gt;, Q&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;/sub&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#160;and&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;[M&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;, M&lt;sub&gt;y&lt;/sub&gt;, M&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;/sub&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#160;are the shear force and bending moment along x-y-z-axes respectively (&lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#160;and&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#160;are applied load and moment).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To find&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;Slope&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#160;and&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;Deflection&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/31389737/42560803-2e2ea592-8515-11e8-81cc-b511e1286ff5.png" rel="noopener"&gt;&lt;img alt="def_1" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/31389737/42560803-2e2ea592-8515-11e8-81cc-b511e1286ff5.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/31389737/42560832-466c2986-8515-11e8-9ac7-4a0939a41a52.png" rel="noopener"&gt;&lt;img alt="def_2" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/31389737/42560832-466c2986-8515-11e8-9ac7-4a0939a41a52.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
where&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;[w&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;, w&lt;sub&gt;y&lt;/sub&gt;, w&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;/sub&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#160;and&amp;#160;&lt;em&gt;[&amp;#952;&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;, &amp;#952;&lt;sub&gt;y&lt;/sub&gt;, &amp;#952;&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;/sub&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#160;are deflection and slope along three axes respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example for the API:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a beam of l meters long. A constant distributed load of magnitude q&lt;br /&gt;
is applied along the y-axis from start till the end of the beam. A constant distributed&lt;br /&gt;
moment of magnitude m is also applied along the z-axis from start till the end of the beam. Beam is fixed at both of its end. So, deflection of the beam at the both ends&lt;br /&gt;
is restricted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from sympy.physics.continuum_mechanics.beam import Beam_3d
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from sympy import symbols
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; l, E, G, I, A = symbols('l, E, G, I, A')
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b = Beam_3d(l, E, G, I, A)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.apply_support(0, "fixed")
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.apply_support(l, "fixed")
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; q, m = symbols('q, m')
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.apply_load(q, dir="y")
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.apply_moment_load(m, dir="z")
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.shear_force()
[0, -q*x, 0]
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.bending_moment()
[0, 0, -m*x + q*x**2/2]
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.solve_slope_deflection()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.slope()
[0, 0, l*x*(-l*q + 3*l*(A*G*l**2*q - 2*A*G*l*m + 12*E*I*q)/(2*(A*G*l**2 + 12*E*I)) + 3*m)/(6*E*I)
+ q*x**3/(6*E*I) + x**2*(-l*(A*G*l**2*q - 2*A*G*l*m + 12*E*I*q)/(2*(A*G*l**2 + 12*E*I))
- m)/(2*E*I)]
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.deflection()
[0, -l**2*q*x**2/(12*E*I) + l**2*x**2*(A*G*l**2*q - 2*A*G*l*m + 12*E*I*q)/(8*E*I*(A*G*l**2 + 12*E*I))
+ l*m*x**2/(4*E*I) - l*x**3*(A*G*l**2*q - 2*A*G*l*m + 12*E*I*q)/(12*E*I*(A*G*l**2 + 12*E*I)) - m*x**3/(6*E*I)
+ q*x**4/(24*E*I) + l*x*(A*G*l**2*q - 2*A*G*l*m + 12*E*I*q)/(2*A*G*(A*G*l**2 + 12*E*I)) - q*x**2/(2*A*G), 0]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this class is relatively new, it would require a few improvements in the future:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As&amp;#160;&lt;code&gt;Beam_3d&lt;/code&gt;&amp;#160;doesn&amp;#8217;t use&amp;#160;&lt;code&gt;SingularityFunction&lt;/code&gt;, I was unable to find a way to represent point load/moments. So for now&amp;#160;&lt;code&gt;Beam_3d&lt;/code&gt;&amp;#160; only supports continous load (applied over the whole span length of beam).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also,&amp;#160;This class assumes that any kind of distributed load/moment is&lt;br /&gt;
applied throughout the span of a beam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, after discussing it with Arihant, we decided to raise NotImplementedError in such cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next Week&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure PR&amp;#160;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/14883"&gt;#14883&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;gets merge by the end of next week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start implementing plotting methods for Beam class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
